你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到pwn学院的另一个模块
welcome to another module in pwn College
这是内核模块的开头
this is the beginning of the kernel module
这个模块将会是一次非常有趣的经历
this module is going to be a very interesting experience
它将把我们带入一个不同的层次
it's going to take us into a different level of abstraction
相较于我们一直所处的
than where we've been operating until now
希望你会喜欢这趟旅程
hopefully you will enjoy this ride
什么是内核
what is a kernel
我是在2020年美国大选前不久，录制的这段视频
I'm recording this lecture shortly before the 2020 United States general election
所以我会用一个基于美国环境的类比
so I will use a US centric analogy
如果你是外国人，那很抱歉
apologies if you are watching this from outside of the country
从美国视角看
but basically in a US centric view
你可以这样想
you can imagine
独立的进程就像独立的州
individual processes are basically individual states
每个州管理它们自己的内部事务
and individual states manage their own affairs internally etc etc
但联邦政府，计算机的内核
but the federal government which is the kernel
会管理不同州之间的互动
manages the states interactions with each other
还有外部资源，外交等等
and with external resources other countries and so forth
这是一个很好的类比吧
that's a good analogy right
那么只有内核才能访问的外部资源是什么呢
and so what are these external resources that only the kernel has access to
有几个可以直接用的例子
we have several immediate examples we can use
在计算机中
in computing
共享资源基本就是你的计算机
a shared resource is basically your computer nowadays
即使你不与其他人共享你的电脑
even if you don't share your computer with other people
计算机上的进程彼此共享计算机的硬件
the processes on your computer share the computer the hardware with each other
当然很多时候
and then often times of course
如果你在使用服务器
if you are in a on a server or whatever
你会与其他人共享服务器
you share that server with other people
我们来看看指令
so let's look specifically at instructions
有哪些仅供内核使用
what are these kernel-only
非常敏感的
very sensitive instructions
需要被保护以防进程随意使用的指令
that need to be protected against just basically unfettered use by individual processes
其中一个指令就是HLT
one such instruction is hlt
hlt会关闭CPU计算
hlt shuts down that should say CPU computation
只是停止了
just stops it
实际上并没有关闭系统
it doesn't actually turn off the system
它只会让CPU停止工作
it just stops the CPU until
关闭系统还需要做更多
there's more work to be done
但这个指令
but this is a instruction that
应该只有硬件管理者能执行
really only the manager of the hardware should be making
这个管理者就是内核
that manager is the kernel
有些指令直接与硬件外设交互
there're instructions were interacting directly with hardware peripherals
两个这样的指令，in和out，分别用于输入和输出
two such instructions are in and out for input and output
它们是用来与
they are used to communicate with
如，你往电脑上插的小卡片，通信的
like the little cards you plug into your machine
其他交互技术也是保留给内核使用的
among other interaction techniques that are also reserved for kernel use
还有一些外部资源
and then there's actually a bunch of
不光是指令，还有特殊寄存器
not only instructions but also special registers
例如
for example
控制寄存器3
control register 3
CR3记录着页表信息
cr3 is a reference to the page table
它用于
that is used to
将进程的虚拟地址
translate virtual addresses of your process
转换为实际内存中的物理地址
into physical addresses in your actual RAM
就在你电脑里的内存条里
right in the RAM stick inside your computer
你可以在维基百科上读到更多
you can read more about them on Wikibedia it's a
或者在互联网上的很多地方
or many many places around the internet
不管你信不信，这个寄存器能直接用mov访问
but it's a register that can just be accessed using mov believe it or not
但是只能在内核模式下访问
but can only be accessed in kernel mode
因为如果你能控制CR3寄存器
because if you could control the CR3 register
基本上你可以
you could basically
任意控制进程的内存映射
arbitrarily control the memory mappings of your process
然后你就可以修改你的系统内存
and then you could clob your system memory
做各种各样的坏事
and do all sorts of bad stuff
所以CR3只能由内核控制
so CR3 is only controllable by the kernel
类似地，有一个特殊的寄存器叫做MSR_L STAR
in a similar vein there's a special register called MSR_L STAR
它是基于特定模式的寄存器
it's a Model-Specific Register
长模式 系统调用 目标 地址 寄存器
Long mode Syscall Target Address Register
这个寄存器
this is the register that
记录了系统调用会跳转到那里执行
defines where the syscall instruction transfers control flow to
通常是在内核内部
usually that's inside the kernel
显然，如果你能设置它
obviously if you could set that
你就可以截取所有的
then you could intercept all sorts
你会造成很大的破坏
you could wreak a lot of havoc
原因很多，稍后会讲到
for a lot of reasons that you'll go into later
有两个指令
and there are two instructions
wrmsr和rdmsr是用来访问这个寄存器的
writemsr and readmsr that are used to mess with this register
当然
and of course
这些指令也仅供内核使用
these instructions are also reserved only for kernel use
现在我们已经将内存分为
now we've established this kind of dichotomy
内核，和用户空间
where you have the kernel you have user space
这两者是不相等的
and the two are not equivalent
我来调节一下音量
so let me adjust volume
我刚刚注意到声音有点大
I just now notice it's getting a little crazy
那么你的电脑是怎么知道
so how does your computer know
你是否能运行
if you are allowed to run
你是否可以访问CR3寄存器
if you're allowed to touch the CR3 register or not
如果你执行 mov CR3, rax
if you do mov CR3 rax
它怎么知道该不该让你执行呢
how does it know whether to let you do that
当CPU执行时
the CPU as it's executing
会记录当前正在执行的权限级别
tracks the privilege level at which you're currently executing
这个权限级别被分成不同圈层，不同的环
and this privileged level is split into rings
这是基于x86的
this is again an x86 centric view of things
有的架构有很多环
there are architectures with many rings
有的架构不用环的概念
there are architectures don't use the terminology of rings
有的架构只分2个环
there are architectures with only two rings
实际上
realistically
X86只使用两个半环
x86 you only kind of use two and a half rings
接下来会讲到这个半环
I'll go into the half next but
历史上有这四个环
historically there have been these four rings
0环
ring 0
实际上
actually
我们先从熟悉的用户层开始
let's start from user space which we are familiar with
3环是最外面的环
ring 3 the outermost ring
最小权限环
the least privilege ring
我们在整个课程中都处在这个环中
we've been living in this ring throughout this entire course
这里有很多限制
it's very restrictive
你不能设置CR3寄存器
you can't do stuff like set the CR3 register
你不能与硬件外设交互
you can't interact with hardware peripherals
你不能执行HLT
you can't do hlt
有很多很多事情你是不能做的
there's many many things you're not allowed to do
但足以运行谷歌浏览器
but you know that's still enough to run Google Chrome
还有cs等等
and another advanced counter strike and so forth
非常酷的软件
very cool advanced software
当然
and of course
当软件在这个环上运行时
when this software running in this ring
需要和系统交互时
it needs to do anything in terms of interactive with the system
它需要和1环交互（口误）
it needs to talk to ring 1
还有2环和1环
there is ring 2 and ring 1
哦，抱歉，它需要和0环交互
oh sorry it has to talk to ring 0
还有2环和1环
so there's ring 2 and ring 1
最初，它们是为设备驱动准备的
they were originally envisioned for device drivers
区分了不同访问级别
of different access levels
也许你想要一些代码能使用in和out指令
maybe you wanted some piece of code that had access to the in and out instruction
但没有权限访问CR3寄存器
but didn't have access to the CR3 register
实际上，它们并没有被使用
realistically they're not used
实际上，在安全性方面，我们没有认真到用上它们
we are not actually that serious about security to actually utilize these
但它们确实存在
but they exist
接下来我会简单讲一下1环的一个用例
and I'll actually talk briefly about a use case for ring 1 for example next
然后是0环
and then you have ring 0
这被称为主管模式
this is called supervisor mode
这里是没有限制的
it's unrestricted
你可以做任何事
you can do anything
你能做一些直接损害硬件的事情
you could do stuff that will directly harm your hardware
你可以锁定CPU的
you could lock your CPU's
叫什么来着
what's it called
CPU时钟
your CPU clock
在非常高处
to be very high
关闭温度限制
disable Thermal throttling
取决于你的主板，你可以关掉风扇
and you could shut down fans depending on how fancy your motherboard is
在0环中，如果你真的想，你可以烧掉你的CPU
and you could burn out your CPU if you really wanted to in ring 0
你可以
you can
取决于硬件
depending on hardware
取决于驱动支持等
depending on driver support etc
但你可以做很多
but you can do a lot
你可以很危险
you can be very dangerous
你可以摧毁系统
you can certainly destroy the system
永久性的，或暂时的
whether permanently or temporarily
实际上
realistically
正常情况
normally
这是内核运行的地方
this where your kernel runs
而且它不会破坏你的系统
and does not destroy your system
通常情况下，它能很好地管理一堆模块
normally it manages a peaceful cohabitation of a bunch of modules
一堆用户空间进程
a bunch of your user space processes
以及他们使用的所有资源
and all the resources that they use
类似于操作系统会记录你的uid
and similar to an operating system tracking your user ID
在整个课程中
and throughout this course
你总是关心自己是否以root身份运行
you're constantly concerned with am I running as root
自己的eid是多少
what's my effective ID
实际id是多少
what's my real ID
在解决setuid题目的过程中
with the setuid challenges you've been solving
类似的
similar to that
CPU会记录你当前的特权级别
the CPU tracks your current privilege level
记录当前运行在哪个环上
says okay what ring am I in right now
在用户空间中，你在3环上
in user space you're in ring 3
在内核模式下，你在0环，等等
in kernel mode you're in ring 0 obviously and so on
我们来简单讨论一下这些环
so let's talk briefly about these rings
实际上现在超越了0环
actually we go now beyond ring 0
实际上有一个-1环，我会解释原因
there's actually a ring negative 1 and I'll explain why
只有0环，限制了
the limitations of just having a ring 0
这就是内核所在的地方
that's where the kernel lives
以内核作为系统的终极超级权威
and the kernel is the end to be all super authority of the system
在21世纪初，随着虚拟机的兴起，开始出现裂痕
started showing its cracks in the early 2000s with the rise of virtual machines
虚拟机基本上是在计算机中运行的客户系统
a virtual machine is basically a guest system you run inside your computer
例如，如果你运行的是Linux
for example if you're running Linux
你想要用Windows电脑
and you want the Windows machine
或者你运行的是Windows，想用Linux机器
or if you're running Windows and you want the Linux machine
或者其他的
or whatever
或者如果你是云主机提供商
or if you are a cloud computer provider
你想把虚拟机出租给别人
and you want to rent out virtual machines to people
基本上，你有一个服务器
you basically have a server workstation
上面有个操作系统，即宿主机操作系统
on which you have an operating system that is the host operating system
在它里面
and inside that
各个虚拟机中，运行着不同的客户机操作系统
in virtual machines run different guest operating systems
你可以将它们授权给别人使用
that you can grant access to
这些客户机操作系统
these guest operating systems
不应该对你的硬件有无限制的访问权限
should not have unlimited access to your hardware
这说得通
this makes sense
如果它们对你的硬件有无限制的访问权限
if they had unlimited access to your hardware
他们就可以
they could
如果他们有真正的0环访问权限
if they had true ring 0 access
他们就可以关掉你的机器
they could shut down your machine
他们可以做很多
they could do a lot of stuff
你不想让客户机操作系统
that you don't want a guest operating system
不想让客户虚拟机，对宿主机做的事情
a guest virtual machine doing to your host system
所以在21世纪初虚拟机刚出现时的解决方案
so the solution in early 2000s when virtual machines first came about
大概是首个版本的VMware出现的时候
and this is kind of when the first version of VMware and so forth came about
是以一种有趣的方式进行虚拟化
was to virtualize in this interesting way
强制客户机内核进入1环
by forcing the guest kernel into ring 1
客户机内核将在1环中运行
and the guest kernel would run in ring 1
大多数时候都是正常的
and many many things would actually work
它可以切换到3环上
and it could switch into ring 3
也可以在3环切换回来
and ring 3 could switch back and so forth
但是当它要切换到
but when it would switch into
当它想执行需要0环权限的操作时
when it was tried to do functionality that relied on ring 0 access
事情会变得一团糟
things would go haywire
因为它不在0环中运行
because it's not running in ring 0
CPU会拒绝运行它
the CPU would refuse to run that
它就会崩溃
and it would crash
所以所有这些消耗大、复杂的
so then all of these costly complex
基本上是软件模拟的方法
basically software emulation methods
需要在客户机操作系统中模拟0环
needed to be used to simulate ring 0 functionality inside the guest OS
这有很大的性能开销
this had a lot of performance overhead
而且非常复杂
and just a lot of complexity
于是发明了一种现代的解决方案
so a modern solution was invented
我们有主管模式
so we have the supervisor mode
它是用于运行内核的
which is what the kernel runs
它是0环
this is ring 0
我们现在发明了hypervisor模式
we have now as a society invented hypervisor mode
它基本上运行在0环以下
this runs basically under ring 0
能够拦截某些敏感动作
and is able to intercept certain sensitive actions
不再需要软件模拟
without having to do software emulation stuff
纯粹的硬件支持
purely in hardware
并在宿主机操作系统中处理它们
and handle them in the host os
比如在虚拟机中模拟虚拟硬件访问
so stuff like simulated virtual hardware access in the virtual machine
等等
and so on
这算是开启了现代云计算
so this is what has actually enabled the modern kind of cloud compute paradigm
硬件上的hypervisor模式，使用了Intel的VTX技术
this hypervisor mode in hardware using stuff like Intel's VTX
好像叫虚拟技术扩展，等等
Virtual Technology Extensions maybe and so on
在本模块中，我们不会讨论hypervisors
we're not going to talk about hypervisors in this module for sure
但你应该注意到它的存在
but it's just something that you should be aware is there
那么这和现代操作系统有什么关系呢
so what does this have to do with modern operating systems
这与现代操作系统有很大关系
it has a lot to do with modern operating systems
显然，这就是现代操作系统的工作方式
obviously this is how modern operating systems work
但是他们使用这些环的方式
but the way that they use these ring system
这种环范式等等的方式
this kind of ring paradigm and so forth
是不同的
is different
所以有不同类型的操作系统
so there are different types of kind of operating system genres
这基本上取决于内核是如何
and it basically depends on how the kernel
操作系统的核心是如何
the very core of the operating system
与其驱动程序交互
interacts with its drivers
并与用户空间程序交互的
and interacts with user space program
对不起
excuse me
我们在这门课中要接触的系统当然是Linux
the typical system that we are dealing with in this course of course is Linux
Linux和freebsd之类的
Linux and things like freebsd and so forth
它们是宏内核
they are monolithic kernels
只有一个内核二进制文件
there's a single kernel binary
它运行在0环
that runs in ring 0
处理所有操作系统级别的任务
that handles all OS level tasks
当有一个驱动
and when you have a driver
比如显卡驱动
for a graphics card
声卡驱动
for a sound card
或文件系统驱动
for a file system
通常，它们会作为模块加载到内核中
typically these are loaded as modules inside your kernel
和内核一样运行在0环
running with the same you know inside ring 0
还有一种操作系统叫微内核
there's another type of operating system called microkernel
微内核
micro kernel
主要用于，要么是安全至关重要的情况
which is mostly used either in security critical situations
比如sel4
such as sel4
或是玩具内核中
or in toy kernels
比如Linux的祖先Minix
such as Minix the ancestor of Linux
微内核系统，有一个运行在0环的微小内核
a micro kernel has a tiny core that runs in ring 0
它是唯一在0环中运行的
and it's the only thing that runs in ring 0
其他的一切
everything else
驱动程序、用户空间程序等等
drivers user space programs and so forth
都运行在低权限环上
they run in less privileged rings
看风格
depending on the flavor
可能都运行在3环
can be either just everything runs in ring 3
当他们需要和硬件通信时
and when they need to do something like talk to the hardware
它们实际上会查询在0环中运行的内核
they will actually query the kernel running in ring 0
让它代表他们与硬件通信
and ask it to talk to the hardware on their behalf
微内核只用于特定情况
this is only used really in niche situations
因为很慢
because it's slow
所有这些环之间的通信，很慢
all of this communication between rings
不同组件之间的通信，很慢
communication between different components
驱动程序将硬件交互分派给内核
the fact that a driver has to dispatch hardware interactions to the kernel
而不是作为内核的一部分，自己执行硬件交互
instead of being part of the kernel  and able to perform hardware interactions on its own
会有很高的运行开销
has fairly high run time overhead
所以通常不用微内核
and so it's typically not used
然后还有一些介于两者之间的东西
and then there's something slightly in between
混合内核
there's a hybrid kernel
它有一些微内核特性
where there are some microkernel features
部分操作系统功能存在于用户空间
where some OS functionality really does live in user space
然后出于性能方面的原因
and then for performance reasons
或者兼容性原因
or compatibility reasons
或两者都有
or mix of those
内核空间中还有一个独立的内核组件
there's a monolithic kernel component that lives in kernel space
例如
for example
macOS就是这种Unix内核的混合系统
macOS is a hybrid system of this kind of Unix core
基本上是基于BSD，外加一大堆苹果扩展
basically based on BSD with a whole bunch of apple extensions
你可以把它看作一个混合内核
you can view this as a hybrid kernel
内核是一个宏内核
where that core is a monolithic kernel
这些扩展又有点微内核的味道
and the extensions are have a bit of a micro kernel flavor
Windows或现代Windows是类似的
Windows is or modern Windows is similar
如果你在Windows中做了很多高级事情
if you have done a lot of kind of in depth power user type stuff in Windows
你可能见过kernel32.dll，好像不对，kernel64.dll
you might have seen kernel32.dll probably not kernel64.dll
不太清楚，我不经常用Windows
I don't know I don't really use Windows regularly
还有ntdll
and versus ntdll
这些都是微内核组件
and those are kind of the microkernel components
他们都在用户空间
and then that live inside user space
然后有一个核心
and then there's a core that runs in
一个非常大的核心
a very large core
比微内核大
larger than a microkernel
它运行在0环
that runs in ring 0
关键是
the point is
尽管在大多数情况下
though for most intents and purposes
Linux
甚至像Windows和macOS中许多有趣的部分一样
and even like many interesting parts of Windows and macOS
都有宏内核的风格
have a monolithic kernel flavor
或基本上就是一个宏内核
or just basically are a monolithic kernel
而一个宏内核中
and a monolithic kernel
所有与内核相关的东西
everything that is related to the kernel
所有的这些驱动程序之类的
all these drivers and everything
都是内核
are the kernel
这有什么关系
why is this relevant
这很重要
this is relevant as we'll see
因为这意味着
because that means that
宏内核中设备驱动程序中的任何漏洞
any vulnerabilities in a device driver in a monolistic kernel
都是一个内核漏洞
is a kernel vulnerability
如果你利用了它，你就能完全控制系统
if you exploit that you have complete control of the system
我们来看看
so let's see
正常情况下
you know when things aren't going wrong
是如何在这些环之间切换的
how do you switch between these rings
比如在Linux或者说x86上
let's say in Linux or on x86
每个架构都是不同的
and it's different for every architecture
我主要讨论的是x86_64 amd64架构
I'm talking specially about x86_64 amd64 architecture
我们概述一下
let's have a high level overview
基本上，内核在0环启动
basically your kernel boots in ring 0
在主管模式下
in supervisor mode
当它启动时
as it boots
它会设置MSR_LSTAR寄存器
it sets that MSR_LSTAR register
刚刚说的寄存器
that we had talked about
将其指向内核的一个例程
to point to a routine in the kernel
我们会在下个视频中看到其中的一些
and we actually look at some of this in the next video
它将MSR_LSTAR指向一个例程
it will set MSR_LSTAR to point to a routine
它大致叫作entry_syscall
that is basically called Enter syscall
它将处理系统调用
that will handle the syscall
当用户空间进程想要与内核交互时
when a user space process wants to interact with kernel
它会调用系统调用
it calls syscall
你已经做过无数次了
you have done this a million times
当调用syscall时会发生什么
what happens when you call syscall
一是
well one thing that happens is
进程的特权级别切换到ring 0
your privilege level of your process switches to ring 0
另一件事是
another thing that happens is
控制流跳转到MSR_LSTAR的值
control flow jumps to the value of MSR_LSTAR
跳转到内核中系统调用处理程序的入口点
to the entry point of the syscall handler in the kernel
现在你
now you are
以前只要调用syscall，事情就奇迹般地发生
used to just calling syscall and things magically happen
但在底层
but under the hood
它就是另一个call
it's just another call
这是一个有点特别的call
it is a call that's a little special
第三件事是
the third thing it does is
它将返回地址保存到寄存器RCX中
it saves the return address into the register RCX
而不是把它放到栈上
rather than putting it on the stack
为什么会这样
why is this
因为栈是不可信的
because the stack is kind of untrusted
可能同时有另一个线程
you could have another thread that is at the same time
在用不好的方式扰乱栈
messing with the stack in some not good way
这会引起大问题
and you know causing big issues
所以把返回地址放入RCX
so you put the return address into RCX
就这些
and that's it
它还做了一些其他杂七杂八的
I mean it does a couple of other housekeeping tasks
我相信也都很重要
that I'm sure are very important
实际上，你可以点击这个链接
and you can actually follow this link
获取syscall指令的伪代码
to get the pseudo-code of the syscall instruction
也许我们应该看看这个链接
actually maybe we should follow the link
我切换到浏览器
let me switch over to a browser
如果我们放大这里
if we zoom in here
这是syscall指令的伪代码
this is the pseudocode of the syscall instruction
你可以看到
and you can see
它的作用是
what it does is
它将返回地址放入RCX
it puts the return address into RCX
跳到这个LSTAR
jumps to this LSTAR
LSTAR寄存器中的地址
the address in the LSTAR register
然后它
and then it has
这里
somewhere here
也许这里
here maybe
它将特权级别（CPL）设置为0
it sets the yeah the privilege level to zero
将其设置为0环
sets it to ring 0
所以它就是一个内部的记录
so that's just an internal thing that's tracked
非常简单，对吧?
super straightforward right
这为现代的多进程等等提供了基础
and this enables all of you know modern multi process computing and so forth
知道了特权级切换过程，你几乎可以
knowing this you can almost
显然还有很多要做的
I mean obviously there's a lot to go
但你几乎可以实现你自己的操作系统
but you can almost implement your own operating system
你只要这样做
you just you know do this
总之
anyways
当内核准备返回到用户空间时
when the kernel is ready to return to user space
它会调用对应的返回指令
it calls the appropriate return instruction
如果它调用的syscall
so if it was invoked using syscall
它会调用sysret
it will call sysret
sysret所做的与syscall相反
sysret does what syscall does in reverse
它将特权级别切换为ring 3
it switches the privilege level to ring 3
然后跳转到RCX
and then it jumps to RCX
你也可以在这个网站上查看
and again you can follow over here in this site
上面也有sysret的伪代码
it also has the sysret pseudocode
你可以看到它做了很多其他重要的事情
and you can see it does a lot of other important stuff
但基本上就是这样
but that's basically it
其实很直接
it's actually quite straightforward
我们快速讨论一下内核用户关系
let's talk real quick about the kernel user relationship
基本上
basically
用户空间进程的虚拟内存都在低地址
user space processes have virtual memory at low addresses
这个图片可能看不清
this might be hard to see
取决于屏幕的大小
depending on the size of the screen
但你以前执行cat /proc/self/maps
but you're used to do a cat /proc/self/maps
内存空间映射
the memory space mappings
基本上是
basically they are
所有这些地址都以两个00开头
all of these addresses start with two null bytes
然后是7f等等，甚至更低
and then there is 7f blah blah and lower
比它高的都是内核内存
everything higher than that is kernel memory
你通常不会看到内核内存
and you typically don't see kernel memory
除了映射的这个Vsyscall
with the sole exception of this Vsyscall page that's mapped
我会简单提一下
I'll briefly mention
好吧，我现在就说一下
well I'll mention right now
基本上，它是一个过时的，加快系统调用的优化
it's basically a obsolete optimization for making syscalls faster
现在用得越来越少了
that is used less and less nowadays
基本上，它是一个用户空间可以访问的内核内存页
but this is a kernel page that is accessible to userspace basically
这有点疯狂
which is kind of crazy
内核有它自己的虚拟内存空间
but basically the kernel has its own virtual memory space
与进程虚拟内存空间挨着（不考虑地址高16位）
adjacent to your process virtual memory space
我的意思是，虚拟内存空间是相同的
I mean it's the same virtual memory space
但是内核虚拟内存地址空间在更高处
but the kernel has the high
内核的数据和代码等等都在高地址中
the kernel has its data and code and so forth in high addresses
有趣的是
interestingly
内核态下的类似于syscall指令的系统调用
system calls that like the syscall instruction
不会切换虚拟内存映射之类的
doesn't switch the virtual memory mapping or anything
它所做的就是切换到0环
all it does is it switches into ring 0
然后跳转到指令
and then jumps to an instruction
但
but
通常内核内存不能从3环访问
normally kernel memory is not accessible from ring 3
所以你不能猜一个内核地址，就直接跳转过去
so you can't just guess at that address and jump there
而不先通过合法方式提升到0环
without being allowed to do so by elevating into ring 0
比如syscall
by for example doing a syscall
这就是内核的概述
so that's how the kernel works at a very very high level
显然，我们会在以后的视频中更深入地研究它
we'll dive into it a little more in future videos obviously
我们快速讨论一下内核安全
let's talk real quick about security of the kernel
这是一门安全课程
this is a security course
我们将探索内核漏洞
and we'll be exploring kernel vulnerabilities
不是现在
if not right this moment
现在我只想让你们熟悉内核
right now I just want you to become familiar with the kernel
熟悉交互方法和内核调试
and familiar with interacting and debugging that
熟悉这个环境
this environment and so forth
但最终我们将利用内核中的漏洞
but eventually we'll be exploiting vulnerabilities in the kernel
那么内核中有哪些漏洞呢
so what kind of vulnerabilities are in the kernel
好吧
well
就是很多标准的漏洞
they're the standard many many of the standard vulnerabilities
我们已经讨论过，或将要讨论
that we have talked about and will talk about in this course
内核代码也是代码
code in the kernel is just code
只是它在更高的权限级别上运行
it's just running in a higher privilege level
类似于利用setUID程序
similar to exploiting a setUID executable
只是现在利用的是究极的setuid程序
you are exploiting the ultimate setUid executable
最具有特权的程序
the ultimately privileged executable
通过我们很快会讲到的，特定通信渠道
through very specific communication channels that we'll talk about soon
那么你为什么要
so why might you want to
还有应该如何利用内核呢
and how would you exploit the kernel
你可以从几个方向攻击内核
you can attack the kernel from a number of directions
过去有的攻击
there have been attacks of vulnerabilities in the past
可以从外部触发漏洞
that were triggerable from the outside world
算是集中在过去90年代
back this is kind of more in the domain of the 90s
但从那以后，就只有零星出现
but it's popped up here and there since then
对于这种漏洞，你可以精心制作恶意网络数据包
where you could craft a carefully created malicious network packet
把它发送给目标机器
send it at a machine
目标机器就会崩溃
and the machine would crash
或者可以代码执行
or you would gain code execution
这在Windows 95中经常发生
this happened a lot in Windows 95
这在Linux中也发生过
it has happened in Linux
非常罕见
it's very rare
现在尤其罕见
especially rare nowadays
你可以想象，这样的事情
you can imagine how something like this
要是发生在现在，将非常恐怖
might be extremely extremely terrifying in the modern world
你可以在用户空间发动攻击
you can launch your attacks from userspace
这也是我们这里发动攻击的方式
and this is how we will be launching our attacks
利用一会我调用的syscall处理程序中的漏洞
or launch ?? by exploiting vulnerabilities in syscall handlers I will call
以及我们将要讨论的其他内核接口
and other kernel interfaces that we'll talk about
这是人们逃逸沙盒的一种非常常见的方式
this is a very common way that people escape from sandboxed processes
在沙盒模块中
in the sandboxing module
我提供了一个漏洞库链接
I had linked to a repository of vulnerabilities
沙盒逃逸的各种漏洞
sandbox escape vulnerabilities
他们中的大多数
the majority of them or very very many of them
实际上利用了
actually exploit a
使用的攻击向量是，从沙盒到内核的接口
use an attack vector from the sandbox into a kernel interface
出于性能原因，沙盒允许这样做
that is allowed by the sandbox for performance reasons
最终利用内核接口中的漏洞
and exploit a vulnerability in the kernel interface
一个有趣的攻击向量是
and an interesting attack vector is
从你插入的设备，发起漏洞利用
launching exploits from devices that you plug in
有很多这样的例子
so there have been many examples
系统没处理好外围设备
of systems that don't handle peripherals properly
这个处理也只是比特数据的交换
that's also just an exchange of bits
所以你可以买一个设备
so you can buy a device
一个可编程u盘
a programmable USB stick
比如teensy
like the teensy for example
给它编一个攻击程序
program it carefully with an attack
把它插到一些嵌入式设备上
plug it into some embedded device
实现代码执行
and achieve code execution
非常酷
it's very cool
你想利用攻击做什么
what do you want to do with an attack
如果你从外面发起攻击的话
if you were launching it from the outside actually
你可能希望在机器上实现持久化控制
you might want to achieve persistence on the box
你可能想找存在感
you might want to achieve a presence
你插入一个teensy
you plug in a teensy
然后在你的游戏主机上执行代码
and suddenly of code execution running on your game console or something
如果你从用户空间发起攻击
if you are launching it from user space
通常
you typically
要么是想提升特权级别
either want to escalate your privileges
要么是希望在系统中安装rootkit
or you want to install a root kit in the system
在内核中隐藏一些恶意程序
to kind of hide some maliciousness inside the kernel
或者让其它进程找不到它
or hide it from other processes
或者你可能想要使用内核
or you might want to use the kernel
利用其对硬件不受限制的访问权限
and its unfettered access to the hardware
更进一步
to go further
我给大家举一个例子
so I'll leave you with one example of this
2016年
in 2016
一个自称迈克·披萨的安全研究员
a security researcher calling himself Mike Pizza
在华为P9手机上进行了一连串漏洞利用
used a crazy chain of exploits on a Huawei P9 phone
当时很现代化的手机
very modern phone at the time
首先通过正常方法安装一个正常的Android应用程序
started with a normal Android application installed through normal methods
该应用程序
that application
利用了华为P9系统进程中的漏洞
exploited a vulnerability in a system process on the Huawei P9
获得了root权限
to achieve root access
从此应用程序便有了root权限
from there the application now having root access
对内核有了差不多是不受限制的访问权限
had more or less unfettered access into the kernel
它可以进行任意的系统调用等等
it could make arbitrary system calls and so forth
迈克·披萨利用这个能力
and mike pizza use that capability
利用了一个内核漏洞
to exploit a kernel vulnerability
获得了内核内的代码执行
to gain code execution inside the kernel
使用这个内核中的代码执行
used that execution that presence inside the kernel
攻击了，附加安全设备中运行的应用程序
to attack an application running on an attached security device
信任区域
Trust Zone
一个独立的处理器
a separate processor
附加在手机常规处理器之外运行
running attached to the processor typically present on your phone
信任区域，管理指纹身份验证之类的事情
the Trust Zone handles things like fingerprint authentication
然后迈克·披萨通过破坏信任区内核攻击了它
which then mike pizza attacked by compromising the trust zone kernel
并且能够使用信任区域内核
and being able to use that trust zone kernel
修改实际指纹模块
modify the actual fingerprint module
让他解锁手机
to allow him to unlock a phone
只要把他的鼻子贴在指纹传感器上
just by pressing his nose against the fingerprint sensor
这非常疯狂
this is a very crazy stuff
基本上涉及两个内核漏洞
involving basically two kernel vulnerabilities
还有两个应用程序漏洞
and two application vulnerabilities
一个应用程序漏洞，用来获得Android设备的root访问权限
one application vulnerability to get root access into Android device
一个内核漏洞，用来进入内核
then a kernel vulnerability to get into the kernel
然后一个漏洞，用来进入信任区域的用户空间
then a vulnerability to get into the Trust Zone user space
然后进入信任区域的内核
and then into the Trust Zone kernel
并从信任区域内核，攻击信任区域中另一个应用
and from that TrustZone kernel into another TrustZone application
这是一种
this is the kind of thing that
我们现在拥抱的
we are now opening up to
这真的是在计算机系统中畅游无阻
this is the world of truly flowing all throughout a computer system
并尽可能获取漏洞能提供的一切价值
and getting everything you can out of the vulnerabilities present
下个视频见
see you in future videos